Hey look at that. I can control blackout
from my phone. You may
already be familiar with MIDI
control in blackout, but blackout also
supports OSC, which stands
for open sound control and
isn't limited to the 8 bits that MIDI is.
Open sound control is
awesome because a wide range
of hardware and software supports it and
it allows for custom
messages so the possibilities
are endless. In this video I'm going to
show you how to set up OSC
with an app called Touch OSC.
Touch OSC is free on your computer so you
can download it there and
start playing around with
it and follow along with the video, but
everything we're going to
learn about the connection setup
translates to any OSC device or software
you're going to use. You
can even go crazy and start
hooking up game controllers or building
your own faders. So the first thing
you're going to want
to do is check that blackout and your OSC
device are on the same
network. I can come up here to
link status in blackout and I can see my
network here and then on my
phone I can see that I'm on
the same network. I'm on Android so if I
click this little wheel I
can come down here to view
more and see my IP address. This will be
useful for later so I'm going to keep
this number memorized.
Then back in blackout I'm going to
connect device and go to the OSC tab. The
first thing I'm going
to do is click on OSC documentation. If
you're connected to the
internet you'll be taken to the
blackout web page where you can see all
of the messages in blackout.
I'm going to scroll down to
the fader commands and we'll start by
controlling the global fader level of
fader one. So this is
the message that I'll need to put in
touch OSC and I can see here in the
arguments it's going to be
an integer from 0 to 255. So let's see
what all of that means. I'm
going to open touch OSC on my
phone and then I'm going to press and
hold in the middle and add
a fader. I'll make it a bit
bigger here by just dragging it around.
With my fader selected I'll
hit this bar graph icon and
make sure that in the documentary here my
fader is still selected
and I'll scroll down to where
I can see the messages. For now I'll
delete the MIDI message out
by clicking the X and then I'll
tap on OSC. Now in this section where it
says address this is
where I'm going to put the OSC
path from the blackout documents. I'm
going to start by pressing
holding name here and deleting
it by clicking OK then I'm going to touch
the slash. In the slash
I'll write exactly what was
in the blackout page. So I'll do slash
BLK slash fader slash global
slash now here's where I put
the number I'll do fader one slash level
and then I'll click enter. Then in
arguments you'll see
here it says float I'm going to change
the conversion to
integer and I'll send it from 0
to 255 because again that's what the
documentation tells us to do. After
hitting enter I'm going to
come up to link and go into OSC. Now I
already have some things
configured but I'm going to double
check that it's exactly what blackout's
expecting. In the host I'm going to put
the IP address of my
iPad. Once again looking at the blackout
page I can see my IP
address 192.168.0.2 and then this
part's a bit of a brain teaser so up at
the top here where it says
blackout receive address and
port we see that the port is 9003 so
that's what I want my send
port to be in touch OSC and I'll
make sure that's 9003. Then down in
blackout this is where it's
going to be sending any fader
feedback to my touch OSC device so I'm
going to change this to the
IP address of my phone which
was 192.168.0.19 and then I'll want the
port to match touch OSC's
receive port at 9006 so we'll
make sure that's configured in both and
then I'll click done. Now
back in touch OSC I'll hit these
bar graphs I'll close out of link status
in blackout and now I'll
hit this play button. As
I move the fader on my phone you can see
it moves in blackout and if
I move the fader in blackout
you can see touch OSC follows. Now let's
add a button give myself
some more room on the canvas
here and I'll press and hold in the
middle of the canvas and add a button.
This is going to be the
same process I'll hit the bar graph I'll
scroll down delete MIDI and
come into my button messages
and come into the OSC messages I'll
delete name by pressing holding I'll come
to the slash and now
I'll navigate back to the OSC
documentation and let's add one of the
action buttons so we'll do
slash BLK slash fader slash global slash
one slash key underscore one
and I'll hit enter. I'll hit the
X to check the arguments and here we can
see it already matches it's
expecting a float of 0 or 1.
I'll hit the bar graphs to get out of
this menu and then I'll hit
play again. I'll navigate back
to blackout and since we're already
linked up I can see as I hit
the button the toggle works
and as I move the fader the fader works.
So that was a super brief
overview of how to set up OSC
using touch OSC but the process is the
exact same for any OSC
device. You match IP addresses and
ports and you give it the arguments
blackout is expecting. Take a look at the
full OSC documentation
on our website you can map OSC to any
control and blackout it's awesome you're
gonna love it let me
know in the comments what you want to see
more of and I'll see you next time.